<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>SVG::Graph</title>

  <subtitle>@ANT_VERSION@</subtitle>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>@ANT_DATE@</date>

    <author>
      <firstname>Sean</firstname>

      <surname>Russell</surname>

      <email>serATgermaneHYPHENsoftwareDOTcom</email>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1>
    <title>What is it?</title>

    <para>SVG:::Graph is a pure Ruby library for generating charts, which are
    a type of graph where the values of one axis are not scalar. SVG::Graph
    has a verry similar API to the Perl library SVG::TT::Graph, and the
    resulting charts also look the same. This isn't surprising, because
    SVG::Graph started as a loose port of SVG::TT::Graph, although the
    internal code no longer resembles the Perl original at all.</para>

    <para>SVG::Graph isn't only for charts. With version 0.4.0, support for
    Plot charts was added, so scalar data may now be charted.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>What's new?</title>
    <para>You can find that out in the <ulink 
        href='changelog.html'>change log.</ulink></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Screenshot</title>

    <para>Gotta have one.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/pie.svg" format="SVG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Here's a PNG version of the above image for the
    SVG-challenged:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/pie.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The SVG version is <emphasis>much</emphasis> cooler. <ulink
    url="screenshots.html">More screenshots are available</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Why use it?</title>

    <para>If you're a Ruby programmer, you can't use SVG::TT::Graph directly.
    This package is for you.</para>

    <para>If you want one of the features that this package has that the Perl
    version doesn't, and you don't mind doing your graph code in Ruby, then
    this package is for you.</para>

    <para>If you want to generate SVGs that aren't CSS styled (and work with
    more SVG renderers), use this package.</para>

    <para>If you're a Perl wienie or you have something against Ruby, use
    SVG::TT::Graph. If it doesn't provide you with the features you want, hack
    it yourself.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Getting it</title>

    <para>The source archives contain the example script(s) and an install
    script. Documentation must be downloaded separately.<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://www.germane-software.com/archives/svg_graph_@ANT_VERSION@.tgz">Gzipped
          sources</ulink></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://www.germane-software.com/archives/svg_graph_api_@ANT_VERSION@.tgz">Gzipped
          documentation</ulink></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://www.germane-software.com/archives/svg_graph_@ANT_VERSION@.zip">Zipped
          sources</ulink></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://www.germane-software.com/archives/svg_graph_api_@ANT_VERSION@.zip">Zipped
          documentation</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Why?</title>

    <para>The SVG::TT:Graph package is just fine. It lacked a couple of
    features that I wanted, and it was in Perl<footnote>
        <para>Perl is from Hell. The language is bad enough, but working with
        the package system -- CPAN, etc. -- is an excercize in masochism. I'd
        rather chew on glass.</para>
      </footnote>, so I re-implemented it.</para>

    <para>SVG::Graph is not a straight port of SVG::TT::Graph, because the
    Perl version uses templates, and I don't believe that this is a job for
    templates. Templates are great when you have lots of context containing a
    little bit of evaluated code, but the Graph classes are mostly code with a
    little SVG; therefore, it makes more sense (and is a hell of a lot more
    readable) to have the SVG embedded in the code rather than vice versa.
    However, some of the logic was directly cut and paste out of
    SVG::TT::Graph, as was the entire CSS code and chunks of the
    documentation, and the part of the API that the user sees is almost
    identical to the original.</para>

    <para>In version 0.2.0 I completely refactored the code to make it more
    modular. As a result, the core Graph class contains most of the graph
    drawing primatives, and the specializations (Bar, BarHorizontal, Line,
    Pie, etc.) only draw the plot itself. This results in many fewer lines of
    code, and that code is more robust. SVG::TT::Graph re-implemented most of
    the code for every plot type, whereas SVG::Graph reuses most of the
    code.</para>

    <para>I intend SVG::Graph to have more features than SVG::TT::Graph, which
    is the main reason for the re-implementation. One such feature is the
    ability to change the stacking of the data sets. For instance, SVG::Graph
    allows you to place the data bars from multiple data sets on the same
    graph side-by-side, rather than overlapping.</para>

    <para>SVG::Graph also has an option to disable CSS styling of the graphs.
    This has a number of consequences, both positive and negative. The SVGs
    generated can be larger without CSS, and they are harder to dynamically
    style (you can't use your own styles with CSS disabled). However, a number
    of SVG renderers do not support or do not fully support CSS in SVG (KSVG
    in Konqueror and librsvg, for instance). Adobe and Batik both support CSS,
    so if those are your targets, you can use CSS. For maximum compatability,
    disable CSS with the :no_css attriibute.</para>

    <para>The currently supported graph types are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Bar</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>BarHorizontal</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Line</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Pie</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Plot (this is scalar data)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>TimeSeries (also scalar data, with one axis being dates)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Schedule (scalar time range data, with non-scalar Y axis)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Dependancies</title>

    <para>REXML 3.0+, or Ruby 1.8+. If you want to use the SVG compression
    feature, which generates zlib compressed SVGs, you must also have the Ruby
    zlib library installed.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>There's API documentation available, either <ulink
    url="http://www.germane-software.com/software/SVG/SVG::Graph/doc">online</ulink>
    or for <ulink
    url="http://www.germane-software.com/archive/svg_graph_api_@ANT_VERSION@.tgz">download</ulink>.
    Or, you can use rdoc to generate it yourself. The API documentation is
    pretty comprehensive (Leo Lapworth did a really good job on the docs, and
    I stole most of them), and there's an example application in the main
    directory.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Notes</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>SVG feature support</title>

      <para>Some SVG renderers (librsvg) do not understand CSS. This is a
      problem with Perl's SVG::TT::Graph, because <emphasis>all</emphasis> of
      the styling of the charts it generates is done with CSS. SVG::Graph is
      able to inline the styles, rendering graphs that are compatible with
      more viewers.</para>

      <para>The Pie chart uses the feGaussianBlur filter to generate the
      shadow, whiich is also unsupperted by some renderers (librsvg). The
      shadow will not look as smooth on those displays, although it will
      render.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Sizes</title>

      <para>The bar charts PNGs tend to be smaller than the uncompressed SVGs.
      In the best case (for PNG), the PNG is 66% of the size of the
      uncompressed SVG.</para>

      <para>For line and pie charts, which are a little more visually complex,
      the SVGs are smaller than the PNGs. In the best case, the PNG is 130%
      the size of the SVG. In the worst case, the PNG is 220% the size of the
      uncompressed SVG.</para>

      <para>The compressed SVGs are always much smaller than the PNGs. In the
      best case (a vertical bar chart), the PNG is 4.4 times the size of the
      compressed SVG, and in the worst case (for a pie chart), it is over 12
      times the size of the compressed SVG.</para>

      <para>These values were measured with inline styled SVGs, and the PNGs
      were reduced to 8-bit, indexed images, and were crushed with
      pngcrush.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Bugs</title>

    <para>SVG::Graph probably contains bugs. In fact, it is probably mostly
    bugs, held together with some working code around them. In particular,
    SVG::Graph is probably really intolerant of *your* bugs, and is likely
    entirely unhelpful in helping you track down problems. We can only pray
    that this situation improves<footnote>
        <para>Prayer is much more effective when accompanied by sums of cash
        sent to the author.</para>
      </footnote>.</para>

    <para>There is a <ulink
    url="http://www.germane-software.com/cgi-bin/roundup/svg-graph">bug and
    feature request database</ulink>; use this, and please create a user
    account if you don't have one, so that I can email you if I have
    questions. Alternatively, post anonymously, and check the database
    often.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Repository</title>

    <para>The sourcecode repository is a <ulink
    url="http://subversion.tigris.org">Subversion</ulink> repository, located
    <ulink
    url="http://www.germane-software.com/repositories/public/SVG">here</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>
</article>
